I'm going to get you set up
with co-host permission
so you can share screen as desired.
Okay, great.
Good to meet you. And thank you.
Yeah.
You're welcome.
Am I sharing?
I don't see it in my window. Yes.
Perfect. No.
Oatmeal.
Are you our hostess with the most us
or hosts with the most?
Either one. I am not supposed to be.
But I may end up being.
Because. What person is not here?
Okay. No worries.
I just need to create five breakout rooms.
Okay.
Some.
You should have the power as co-host,
but if not, let me know.
Tools
and maybe waiting room.
More rigorous.
Create one.
Can you make Bart also a co-host?
Yep. Okay.
Let participants choose.
Okay.
Bart, will you
tell me what to name the rooms?
What are our planet's names?
So. The
first
one, I just dropped the names in the.
Yeah.
Yeah, that would be right.
Good thinking.
Yeah.
Let me close this
and see.
Awesome.
Okay.
But I can run slides,
and you can just tell me to advance
or not.
Does that work for you?
Or do you want to run slides?
What do you mean, run?
Run. Like,
make them go, like, advance the slides.
Oh, yeah. Yeah, sure. Okay.
You can just tell me
and I'll advance it for you.
Yeah.
Text to the
to the. Run.
Other preparations.
Monica?
You good?
Yeah.
Okay, cool.
There. We're moderated.
Were officially moderated.
We did it.
While know. Bart.
Hi, Bart.
This is my collaborative art. He's
wonderful.
Excellent. You guys should.
He's. He's Berlin based,
so you guys should.
Oh, cool. No. Without me. Yeah.
I'm whales based are.
Okay. Nice.
So it's also late for you? Yes.
It is not quite as late as it is for you,
I think.
Yeah, true.
It's 10:45 now, so.
Yeah.
That's for Berlin though, right?
So. Hey.
We know get started until 11.
That's how it goes.
So this is we're going to get started.
This is out of this world.
It's an explanatory workshop.
But as we're waiting for people
to trickle in a little bit
we have a pre activity.
So it's 2075.
And your next teaching assignment
is on the first permanent Martian colony.
And your students
are the first gen born off world.
They've never seen a tree.
They've never felt rain.
They've never breathed air
that wasn't recycled by a machine.
The satellite bandwidth is really janky.
It's limited and spotty and intermittent.
But you've been allowed
five minutes of unrestricted data
to download and replicate
something from Earth's history
to explain to them
what it was like to be human. So.
So some kind of human artifact.
What do you want to download?
Put it in the chat.
What are you going to show your students?
What's three?
Oh, no, I'm uncool.
I'm. I'm chopped.
Uncle, what is A0 three
archive of our own fanfiction.
Okay.
Mary Oliver.
Yes, they're supposed to be
an amazing documentary
coming out very soon about Mary Pink
Floyd.
Like the whole discography,
like all Pink Floyd or like,
would you generate Pink Floyd, the band
like holodeck style?
I get it in five minutes.
Where it.
Commodore 64.
Yes. Yeah.
Oh, nice.
Caitlin. Yes.
Love it.
So you're on in the right place.
This is this workshop is it's you use.
Right. This is a writing workshop.
So you're going to want something to write
with,
like a Google doc or a journal and pen a
no tap.
So please,
while we're waiting and hanging out,
open those and arrange your screen now
so you have something to write with.
This is a participatory workshop.
Generative workshop.
So we're going to do intros.
We'll look at who who we are
why we are doing this.
Methods.
Lunar punk durable skills
transversal competencies.
Do some writing exercises
and then we'll look at tools.
Juppe
SETI exoplanets, more writing exercises.
And at the end we'll have time for Q&A.
And we'll also have time for share ups.
So if you want to read anything
that you generated, hold it to the end
and you can engage then.
So I'm Monica stores
I do methods I'm a poet and researcher
and theorist and PhD student
at Northeastern University.
I'm the woman at MIT fellow,
and I'm the founder of Digital Poetics
Press, the first native literary
small indie press,
in 2019.
I built something called the Augmented
Reality Poetry Machine,
and in 2021, it was sent to Earth's moon
as part of a larger
lunar payload delivery.
And this sparked my interest
in space art in the space humanities.
So I set out to
learn all I could about space
art and space humanities.
So what I found was that a lot of the tech
was already operational and arriving.
So to the left,
you'll see the 2023 Asteroid Mining
Company rankings.
And notice the deployment dates.
They've been operational since 2023.
This image at left is now
sub sub stratosphere aircraft carrier
that China is currently developing.
And this is the Europa Clipper,
which is currently and
it's currently in transit to
do flybys
to see if the subsurface of the ocean
can support life on Europa.
But what it noticed was that the cultural
and ethical infrastructures
were completely absent.
This topic is much more urgent
than most people realize.
You notice that the deployment dates,
the mission dates are 2023.
That means when the asteroid
mining operations launched into orbit,
terrestrial harms are already
being repeated in off world contexts.
And if we don't want our future skies
just being
billboards in space,
something needs to be done.
So I started developing lunar punk methods
and frameworks for the space humanities,
and part of
that is building community in this space,
which is how I met my brilliant
and wonderful collaborator Bart.
Take it away.
So I am book covers.
I'm a poet and artist, researcher and
and a lot of other things too.
But we'll keep it this for now.
And I'm currently an artist in residence
at the City Institute where I am.
My collaborators have developed
the project Exoplanet Poetry, and I'm also
doing all kinds of other weird poetry,
like XR poetry and code poetry.
And can I have to decide?
But can I ask you,
what is the study institute
for people who don't aren't familiar?
Yes, the City Institute is the search
for Extraterrestrial Intelligence
Institute and famously,
invented by Carl Sagan
and Frank Drake
and also an early collaborator.
And they do very serious academic
research into I.
And one of the things okay,
so I'm first going to show
just what code
poetry is, just very, very briefly. And
the idea is
that the poetry is code
that can execute itself.
And with that add
something to that, to the phone itself.
And this is
a an example of an execution
of one of the code poems that,
I mean, that I wrote.
And the idea is to,
criticize tech with the use of tech,
because our minds
have been occupied by code,
and that is what the poetry.
And next slide, please.
And, and Monica and I have in common
that we both do a form of, of poetry
and I do augmented reality and writing
in which I try to find
two sides of the same topic,
which I try to write
about in two different layers.
So there's one layer that's on the screen
and the other layer is at it
when you look through your device.
And that is a way to sort of mitigate
this moment of polarization
in which we live, to try to have a text
that can embody multiple viewpoints
at the same time.
And, okay, that has nothing to do
with what we are here for today.
You may your online
this is our project, explanatory poetry.
And what you see here
is a bit of the performance that we did.
Hold on, I lost it.
You may your own life.
You didn't stop there.
You had all sorts of trouble
and it wasn't easy to get lost
and you didn't tell your friends.
So the idea is that.
But not in human language,
but in a language
that might be perceptible
for extraterrestrial intelligence
as they might occur in the universe.
And and so the idea is to write for
species of whom
you have no idea how they perceive.
And, and the idea is to do that
not in human language but in chemistry.
So we try to develop chemistry
as a poetic language.
And and in the next slide,
I will briefly run through
the mechanics of,
of how we set that experiment up.
And so what we try to do is translate
the chemical composition of exoplanet
atmospheres into natural language.
The NASA and the city
keep a large database
of exoplanets, and they have methods to,
to verify which
element chemical elements are present
in the atmospheres of these exoplanets.
And there's lists of that.
And there is of excellence
known to mankind by now.
So there is a large database
and there's a lot of data to work with.
The big question is how do you translate
from chemistry to natural language
to train an AI
that then imposes a speculative being?
You co-create poetry with that AI
that is a placeholder
for the extraterrestrial intelligence.
And the last step is to translate
this human language back into chemistry
so that you could actually have
a poetic conversation
with an express real being.
And so there's a lot of technical details
that I won't go into.
Now, let's go to the fun stuff.
And so this is a poem that
I wrote to get with the AI up,
and which we will introduce briefly.
I won't read it now because I don't think
we have so much time.
Let's do some writing exercises.
So space has totally different
affordances.
How do you explain something
that you don't have language for?
So in the chat
please describe the color blue.
Without any terrestrial references,
you cannot use the word sky,
ocean water, berry,
azure, indigo or cerulean.
So how think of blue.
How do you describe that
with no terrestrial
referencing?
Cool light.
Love that.
Oh, the bandwidth blue on the light
spectrum.
Love it.
All. The tent of the veins
beneath the skin.
Lower end of spectrum.
Human sorrow.
I love that clarity.
My work builds
lunar punk futures,
and I'm operating from the premise
that these are the jetpacks
that we were promised, and it's up to us
to create the future that we want.
The future is participatory,
it is relational.
And my provocation to you
as we engage in this journey
together is what sort of off world future
do you want to see?
What does that look like?
Who is there and how does it get built?
And my the thesis is the future needs you.
In the future is humanity's dependent
stem cells, the how of space travel.
But the humanities solves the why.
I have good news.
Many space
agencies are also thinking about this
and have active research in the loop.
Two words for the thing.
The human capabilities
that they are working with are durable
skills and transversal competencies.
The skills
include interpersonal intelligence,
creative resourcefulness,
metacognitive resilience and systems
thinking and ethical stewardship.
I mean, there's there's a lot more.
So why poetry for space?
Futures is poetry and space.
Space and Exoplanet Future
require capabilities for working
with uncertainties, communicating without
shared reference, noticing assumptions,
adapting across unfamiliar environments,
approaching differences, and poetry
specifically trains for these capacities.
Poetry and the humanities at large
specifically trained
for these critical future skills.
Stem can train for task dependent things,
but the humanities alone
are what teaches and encodes
these intangible
human skills.
Okay, so I want you to
to look at this waveform for a few seconds
and you're going to write two short lists,
what you observe and what you interpret.
Maybe aim for five on each side.
So what do you observe?
What is materially present?
What repeats or changes
where interruptions or silences?
And then I
want you to make a list about what
you interpret.
What do you think this pattern means?
Do you perceive it as intentional
or is it noise?
What assumptions are you bringing to it?
And you don't have to share these out.
These are for you.
NASA's
Humanities and Interstellar Communication
Scholarship is rooting,
rooting us in kind of this kind
of exploratory exercising,
recognizing that patterns
and signals are not
the same as understanding
its meaning, redundancies,
and really highlighting and foregrounding
kind of the human capability
to both assignation of meaning and engage
in sense making.
So I want you to imagine
that you are an astronaut,
and astronauts
experience this,
this kind of transformative moment
when they experience Earthrise and Earth
Light for the first time.
And I want you to imagine
that you are that astronaut,
or that you are a being on
an exoplanet planet observing Earth.
They want you to write,
what does Earth look like
from a distant observer
emotionally, spiritually, ecologically.
If you can't touch
Earth, soil, or breathe its atmosphere,
how does your perspective translate it?
If it helps,
think of yourself
getting in that enclosure,
going through the ignition
and launch process,
moving through atmosphere to stratosphere
to orbit.
And gaining that vantage.
What does empathy look like extended
across light years?
What is planetary sapiens?
Is there planetary sapiens?
Will rest here for a few minutes
as you engage in.
Telling us about the planet
that dreamed of us.
To move on now.
So alien
doesn't mean incomprehensible,
it means differently familiar.
So you're going to write a five line home
using productive constraints.
To to someone something.
Don't use the words human
or alien or language or intelligence.
Don't describe
what you think the receiver looks like.
Don't ask the receiver
to prove that it exists.
Include an offering, an uncertainty,
and leave one line incomplete.
There's a
possible structural template
if you need a little help
imagining what that might look like.
30 more.
To the next.
So in our next
activity, Bart is going to introduce
some exoplanets.
You're going to pick an exoplanet
that speaks to you,
and then you're going to join
the breakout room for that exoplanet.
Hopefully we have enough people to
to to select.
But together with your group
you're going to create a list of 20
features or attributes or imaginings
or speculations
about your planet.
So the the idea is to slowly
place yourself inside one of these
very strange
worlds that are
borderline unimaginable
for us as human beings
and such as Kelt nine B
and which is a gigantic planet
that can reach over 4000°C.
And so if that interests you,
placing yourself in such a hot
environment, for example, and to imagine
what that would do with, with your being,
with your thinking, with your mood, or
then this is the planet for you and
maybe the next one.
Trappist one
is a fairly similar planet to to Earth.
It has an atmosphere,
and there is a feeling
that there might be life,
except that it is a lot colder.
And so if you don't want to go
too far from home,
then this one might be the planet for you.
Monica, can we have the next one?
And K2 18 B
has a thick atmosphere.
It's mostly made out of hydrogen gas
and and,
yeah, it it has also been
named as one of the planets
that might contain life by the,
by the city and one of their focal points.
And then we have the next one,
and that is 55.
Kangri.
That is most certainly not a planet
where we would encounter life
as we know it.
Who knows what other types of life
might be out there?
But this is a planet that has, hot lava
raining from the skies
multiple times a day.
And so this is really
a completely different kind of world where
stone vaporizes
because it is so extremely hard.
And so, you know,
if you want to have a completely different
experience, 55 Cancri is,
might be your new home.
The next one, the last one is Kepler 138
D and is relatively close to home
and and is also about the same size. And
and it might contain a lot of water.
So, this is really a water world.
And in contrast with planets
where all the water
vaporizes immediately,
this planet has a lot of it.
Some of it might be,
steamy and some of it might be frozen,
but that is all to be discovered.
And so
I will invite you to
choose which one of the planets
speaks to you the most.
And and already think about what,
what poetic qualities these planets,
can, can bring to your writing.
And if there's not anyone in your breakout
room, that's okay.
Just generate a list of 20
speculations, imaginings, actual things
about the planet, and what it would be
like inhabiting that planet.
And I think on the next slide.
There are some pointers of things
that you can think about.
Of course.
It's just guidelines.
You can you're free
to imagine anything you like
on your planet, obviously,
but these are things you could.
So light sources, gravity.
If you're on
count nine, Kelt nine B is tidally
locked, right?
Yeah. Yeah. So so what is that like.
So that that means that one
side is always day.
One side is always night.
So how how would that affordance alone
change habitation.
Atmosphere temperature.
How does time function.
What kind of beings live and like
and how they would survive.
How would they interact
with their environment?
And what we think about in explanatory
poetry?
The project is always
what kind of sensors could you have?
What kind of interaction could you have
with the chemistry around you?
That would create some sort of
meaning or something
that we could call life.
And in, in, in strange forms.
Nobody's joining the breakout room, so.
I wasn't sure to join.
I want to join. Oh, no,
I don't know if anyone's in there.
I will reopen them.
Yeah, I didn't know if we were supposed to
join yet.
Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah.
You're you're welcome to.
Oh, let me and let me put this slide
back to. No.
So you can pick your new home.
And you can
you can join them in the the more.
And we can give everyone
like five minutes to generate.
I've never asked you what would you pick.
Which one of these is your first impulse?
You don't have to commit to it.
Well,
during the
forms that we did,
we took the audience to 55 concrete
just because it was such a bizarre.
To which one?
Say again, 55 Cancri.
Okay. Why?
Because this is so
the farthest that you can go from okay.
From Earth,
almost because of this sexual desire
and world with I am melting rocks and
things.
Seas of lava.
But I like it.
They do.
Think.
Nine months ago
there was.
And there might be.
It's like really hard to hear you.
I don't know why.
Oh, really?
No. Yeah.
That is not good.
Can you hear me now?
Trying to find out where the microphone.
Okay, I'm going to close the rooms,
which will close them in 60s.
Or do you want me to give them more time?
We can wait till 25 after.
Okay.
I, I, I think I would pick Kelt nine b.
I'm interested in a the tightly locked and
b want to see what copper skies are like.
I want to know.
I want to know I'm nosy I want to know.
Something.
They're all crazy to imagine.
We've saved
what I think is the best for last.
We have saved a huge special fancy treat
for you guys.
Let me see.
Are we all back?
Yes. Okay.
Welcome back.
Okay. Welcome.
How was it to spend
time on your exoplanet?
Very curious.
What?
But let's do a share out
by the end of it, or.
Yeah.
So this is our tree.
This is our present for you.
This is sort of what
we've been working towards.
And so as I mentioned,
we build an AI that we call Juppe
and that is
that is trained on the chemical data
of the atmospheric,
elements that you of the,
of the exoplanets that I described.
And, and we have tried to find
a mapping of,
of these elements to meaningful text
coming from city papers,
coming from other research papers in the,
in the field of exoplanets
and other things to do with the universe.
And it's trained on our own poetry.
We wrote our own poetry corpus for this
and and it's trained on
we did an open call for poetry,
specifically
about planets
and other things to do with the link.
It put the link in the chat.
So click on that link.
Yes, in and on this link
you can see the result and
and so let me let me check
to make sure I have it right Bart.
So these each the reason we have you pick
an exoplanet is so that you can write
with the Juppe model
that is trained on
the data from that exoplanet.
Okay.
So on the top you can see a dropdown menu.
And there you can select the
the planet that you want to okay.
So if I picked I did Kelt nine B.
So I would input my poetic input here.
And I would generate here to do it's
it's an old fashioned GPT.
So it it mostly finishes your sentences.
So the best thing to do is to give it
an open poetic input.
And, and and it can finish it.
And the idea is explicitly to have an AI
that does not take away
the pleasure of writing.
So that does not take away
the creative process from you
and gives it to the machine.
So the sentence that come out
are not polished, they are rough diamonds.
And it's up to you as a writer to work
your magic
as you would normally do.
And so it's, it's I call it an inspiration
machine more than then.
And so you can take
any of the text that you generated
in the workshop today, any of your lists,
any of the five line poem
with the unfinished lines,
and put that here in the poetic input.
Best to pick if you pick your best line
and you put that in
and you build from that. So.
For example.
The links in the chat
so you, you can play with it yourself.
It's never been used by
so many people at the same time.
Yes, sir.
But let's see.
I believe.
And if you're interested,
the elements, the chemical elements
that are found in the atmospheres of these
exoplanets are listed in the
in the dropdown.
So interesting.
So I had already like I done a poem
and I totally get that it should be open
ended. But I thought just for fun
I'll put the poem in.
So it reproduced the poem exactly,
but added an additional stanza.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
That's typical.
Yeah, that is typical behavior.
Really neat.
Well, it doesn't have to be perfect.
It can be like the listicles.
It can be any.
Text fragments.
Yeah.
Might be the
the load of all those people.
We'll be here till next year.
If you wait for the science fiction
writer to
figure something out, I'm like, okay, so
if it has this kind of mass,
what does that mean that you have to have
in terms of a Nexus skeleton?
And then how would they evolve?
And then that's all part of the model
now Lisle.
That's why we can do
more.
Exactly.
If you really want to be thorough it's
going to take.
I love this
I'm gonna save this one.
We have like 15 minutes left.
We can open it up obviously
to just free flowing discussion Q&A.
Any questions, any thoughts.
If there's any particularly
compelling pieces that you created
during this hour together that you want to
share?
Would love that.
But yeah, the we're open to Q&A now.
Time moves on the exoplanet.
You might
yeah.
You have to just thank you.
You have to just sit
there and be and be patient.
And I believe Bart
said that this many people
had not used the model
at the same time before.
So it's a bit of a stress test
there at a time.
Time is a flat circle, right?
It's Jeremy Balmy, I think you'll find.
Data over the eyes Tuesday nights.
I was going to ask,
what did you what did you all use to
to build this with.
I mean, I'm going to I'm interested
in the nitty gritty.
Well, how do you want to go?
No, it's it's a it's a Pythia model.
Okay.
You chose because it's
a, it's a more ethically trained,
lives.
It's still a relatively small model.
That's that's what we were looking for.
Also,
because of the device, you cannot
see this all trained on our own hardware.
And a lot of the training set
has been written
by by us also ourselves and
in with with the with the city.
Oh, And you are accepting
training data sets.
If anybody has a poetic or writing corpus
they are interested in sharing.
This was done completely with ethical,
transparent and
consent based training
rather than kind of extractive
harm based training of the set.
Putting my email address in the chat.
If anyone would like to share their work
to be incorporated
in the in the training, then
I would be very grateful.
And of course you will be credited.
And incredibly.
Yeah, I mean, this might be a
little bit off base, but I just
it was a really super fun workshop.
I really love that.
And I love the speculative stuff.
And I guess my question,
I guess, is for both of you,
but maybe particularly for Bart,
since I'm really interested in
you being artist in residence for SETI,
that just sounds like the coolest thing
to put on a card.
But to what extent does this workshop
like mirror
the way that you're working
with the scientific data,
or as part of the practice there,
or working with the scientists?
Is is your engagement as as an artist?
They're kind of along these speculative
lines,
like using poetry to break
the certainty apparatus.
Is it kind of what we've seen
in miniature here, or is it very different
working in that space?
No, I think it's
it's it's similar to what
what you've seen.
I mean, I can only scratch the surface
of everything that we have done
with, for example, we have spent,
three, four weeks in total in a, in a lab,
also experimenting with, with chemistry,
sort of going back to, to high school.
That was the last time that I did
physical chemistry,
but we did a lot of experiments to find
what we call sort of a poetic chemical
vocabulary to write poetry with.
And what we did a lot
is, is sort of user feedback loop.
So we, we did experiments based on texts
that we wrote to try
and extract the core emotions from that,
and to map those on chemical reactions
and from those chemical reactions.
We wrote again, poetry inspired by what
we saw and was sometimes truly amazing.
The things that you
love that.
Yeah. So cool. Thank you.
Basic organic chemistry.
So that was
but there's such a strong
layer of semiotics to write
because you had to find
what will substitute for language,
and you settle on chemistry
as the sign, the signifier.
Yeah, yeah, that's the experiment.
And I mean, one of the as I mentioned,
one of the big problems, of course,
is, is the translate one and the other.
And, but we also deliberately chose
poetry and not,
normal communication messages
and to communicate in
because we also believe,
like Monica also said, like
poetry is able to, to express this movie
and to sort of express what you cannot say
directly and live in the lines
and between the official means of,
of communication.
So and for that we feel
it is the best medium to communicate
in with, with the, with like.
Deliberate choice on our part.
And I. Do you have a question?
Oh, sorry.
Yeah,
I guess it's for both of you.
I saw a question
that has kind of popped into my head
sometimes when marveling at the technology
we've created is like,
maybe we are the aliens we're looking for.
And it's it's
just spending all this energy
looking for for someone else.
Who for something else that has done.
I mean, it just seems like the question
itself is a mirror.
Yeah.
And and after the Artemis launch,
there was a lot of people in my life
who had divergent reactions,
who were who were in awe and others
that that shrugged and didn't care.
And I explored that.
And they sense they explained that
it didn't seem like it had a point.
Like, so what if we do go to the moon
or find life or to anything outside of
what's to do here?
And there's curiosity on Earth,
and I think that that's a question
that people,
you know, have explored a lot,
like, let's solve problems here on Earth
now is really just a polite way of saying,
I don't really care about this.
And I think they have a good point.
Like, why should we care about it
beyond the mirror,
which is that
it's in our nature to explore,
because we could be a type of being that
doesn't care about exploration at all,
and we wouldn't even bother to look up
and we would be happy with that.
So I'm just wondering that
in a more abstract space,
if life is closer to like a flower that
blossoms at a place in time for a moment.
Do we have an urgency
to do anything about it?
Do we have an urgency to
survive or spread, or should we just leave
a record that we existed?
Yeah, I love that.
And all of those are really valid,
interesting,
complex points.
My initial framing is like, that's cool.
If it were 1940, 1950 like that,
that ship is sail.
That ship sailed.
Like, did you see that
the asteroid mining company
has been operational since 2023.
Like,
these are no longer speculative things.
These are real.
And so let's not it's not like,
oh, do we want to explore
that that that done happened
like it is happening.
The space billboards are going up.
The patents are already filed.
The question is that is happening.
Now is the time that we have collectively
to decide
how we want that to cement
and foment and ferment.
And it is the very beginning,
very nascent stage.
And so now is the time to make
any adjustments before things, inequities,
the things that we do want
or don't want get, get hard coded in.
Now is the time
where it's still malleable,
where we can change those things.
So it's very understandable that like, oh,
we should be exploring on Earth.
And part of that is a literacy problem,
right?
Like part part of us not understanding
the extent to which this ecosystem
is already funded, operational,
built above, above us right now.
And so part of my
work is starting to figure out
how to close that literacy gap,
because it's it's on purpose that,
that that knowledge gap was left open.
Right.
That was my design.
Yeah. Doctor Fisher yeah.
Yeah.
No, I always Caitlin
I always find it really interesting
when people have limits on like what
people should care about or that
there are like these clear boundaries
between like where we plant our feet
and where we got.
We see.
And I remember
one time
I had this thing for many years
where I would go to
at least one conference a year
that was totally outside my wheelhouse.
And I was in Aspen, and I was
I went to a space thing,
and I thought it was going to be all
people like me, like,
let's find out about, like,
what's happening in space.
And they were like third generation
private space equity people.
They were working on their ships.
They were like, when we had the go around,
it was humiliating where I had to be,
like, pretending like
I was coming in from, like, I'm
the only person there without without,
like, skin in the game of,
like, actively building my world, like my,
my space projects. And it totally changed.
So anyway, just echoing what you just
said, Monica, like, it was fascinating.
I was like, yeah, the political economy.
This is like right now, like these are.
And this was like,
oh, in the last five years.
This is like when my grandfather started
the private space company.
And like, NASA has a private space arm.
I had no idea
NASA has private space stuff.
So yeah, not not a luxury anyway. Totally.
So my provocation to us is like, so.
So what can we do about it?
I one thing that I am doing is,
is this I'm making community.
I'm trying to hold spaces and forums
where we can talk and ideate. I'm
specifically trying to create community
around space humanities and space art.
But like, how can we do this collectively?
Like how, how, how can we enter this?
How can we engage this?
How can we close that knowledge gap?
But so like, please, please
connect with me, with Bart,
with each other because this got to do
got to make it happen.
Absolutely. Thank you so much. Yeah.
One other side to this,
I think Tyler is also that, of course,
you know, in, in in our project,
we talk a lot about
how can you step out
of your anthropocentric
point of view and try to experience
space or communication
without any assumptions
on how the other party is,
is pretty thick.
And and of course,
that is an impossible task because you are
you cannot escape your.
If only because
we have no examples
of what the what that would be like.
So there isn't a mirror at all.
Well it is, it is almost only a mirror
in the sense that that everything else is,
is your executive.
And it tells us in the end
more about who we are.
And of course, that's the boring answer.
But it is.
It is definitely an angle,
I think, that is very deeply engraved
also in our, in our art project.
And of course, the idea
that that other species
you don't have to go to into the universe
to find communication with other species.
Right. It's okay.
And so, so to, to think about that or, or
just communication with other human beings
that don't receive any way
that we and be part of the policy, like,
like if you care
even a little bit about this,
like be part of the policy ideation,
part of part of the making,
the be part of that conversation,
how can we get deeper involved?
I mean,
and today. Yeah.
Follow me in Bart.
Like showing up
today is an excellent start.
The coalition is being built now.
Right.
I'm going to draw us to a close
so that the video team
can start their processing.
But Bart has his email in the chat.
And Monica, I believe as well.
And or you're fairly easy to find.
I am Instagram at Digital Poetics,
at Digital Poetics.
So please do
follow them and keep in touch.
And we're going to end there.
Thank you all very much.
This was excellent. Thank you.
Yay. All right.
We're going to break now.
And we go to the final session
in a little bit,
which is the exhibition
introduction from Dan Cox and yours truly.
Perfect.
Thanks I'll take forever.
All right.
See you guys by me.
And Baka hang out for a few seconds.
If anyone has post post
recording questions
once they.
I think Mel will be melting down the zoom.
Okay, Mel's is going to shut it I think.
Yeah, I think they've got to shut it down.
Thank you.
Recording. Yes. Thank you.
This was delightful.
Thank you I always love these.
Well done. Excellent workshop.
Thank you. Got up.
This was my writing for today, so.
Yeah. Yay!
Thanks, gang.
Okay. Bye bye. Bye. Thank you. Mel.